John Ruskin: Letters to Thomas Goff Lupton
Yale Center for British Art, Rare Books and Manuscripts
- Dated letters, Series I
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, 1855 October 22; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 2 p. (1 folded leaf); 18 x 23 cm. Written in pen and brown ink. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Ruskin's message apparently accompanied a retouched plate, as he remarks upon the parcel of items sent with the letter (plate and "drawings of both it and the glacier"). Ruskin says that he doesn't want the etchings to be dirtied, and will bind this one into his own copy. He adds that the Boys fascimile is "so clear that you will do as well with the glacier drawing." Ruskin gives Lupton instructions for rebiting the plate, referring to strokes that he has added at certain marked places. He asks Lupton to have another plate ready for him when he sends another tracing of a new etching. Ruskin also asks Lupton, "How many mezzotints can you do before Xmas? I want four more," adding that, of these four, two are "comparatively easy." Ruskin closes with a postscript asking Lupton to speak to Cousins about some particular drawings, and telling him to send an impression to him but to keep the plate until Ruskin contacts him again.
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, 1855 November 2; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 p. (1 folded leaf); 19 x 23 cm. Written in pen and black ink, with graphite date written on letter. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Ruskin writes to Lupton asking him to have an item "rolled off" and to "please order the packets of etchings taken, to be sent to me," as well as a plate to be sent to another person for lettering. Ruskin closes: "I should be glad to know that you got safe home and were not washed into the Thames."
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, 1855 November 5; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 2 p. (1 folded leaf); 18 x 23 cm. + envelope. Written in pen and black ink. Previously housed with ALS and envelope labeled "Dec 3" (Box 1, Folder 17). (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Ruskin asks Lupton to "kindly compare [the] enclosed etching with drawing, and give it to Boys with directions as to the way you would like it bitten..." He follows with further specifications about the biting of the plate, which he wishes to be done in such a way as to allow him to make a low toned mezzotint. He asks Lupton to have Boys finish this plate before one entitled "Nottingham," and tells him that he will bring Mr Cousins's check when he next calls. Ruskin mentions that he is writing to his publishers to have a copy of Stones of Venice sent to Lupton. The "Nottingham" image would be published in the fourth volume of Modern Painters.
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, 1855 November 15; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 2 p. (1 folded leaf); 18 x 23 cm. + envelope. Written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Addressed to Lupton at Russell Square. Ruskin discusses a new etching that he has recently received. He notes instructions for altering the image at various points, marked with a series of x's. He asks Lupton to "print 50 copies of it in black and then go on with mezzotint." He writes that the current version is nice but "too light in dis[tance?], I though considering the gravity of work still wanting on the clouds," seeking Lupton's opinion on the same matter. He refers to Boys, telling Lupton that if he thinks the clouds are all right, not to bother Boys with them.
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, [1855?] December 3; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 p. (1 folded leaf); 18 x 23 cm. + envelope. Written in pen and black ink. Previously housed with ALS dated 5 November 1855 (Box 1, Folder 15). (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Ruskin mentions to Lupton that there is a "cheque for 10.10.0" in a copy of a book that he is sending him, and asks him to forward the check to Mr. Cousins. He also remarks that he has been "obliged to spoil another sketch in removing the Plymouth..." explaining that there has been a double sketch. He advises Lupton not to tire himself with the mezzotints, but nevertheless to finish "as soon as you conveniently can the two of sunsets." He says that he wants the sunsets because they are to be included "in the first volume," which he wants to publish on the first of January, and "must have the plates at least a fortnight before."
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, 1855 December 4; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 2 p. (1 folded leaf); 18 x 23 cm. + envelope. Written in pen and black ink. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Addressed to Lupton at Russell Square. Ruskin conveys instructions to Lupton about plates. He says that he has sent two to be bitten, or incised with acid, and makes specific requests about the depth or fineness of etching in various parts of the image. He asks Lupton to "bite all the rest as finely as you can, so as not to run the finer lines into each other..." He writes that he will not mezzotint this etching, but wants another made for mezzotinting, while the first will be "published as it is." He asks for the plates to be returned after impressions are made. He closes by asking Lupton how he is getting on, and says that he has one more "rather elaborate plate to be done before New Year."
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, [1855?] December 6; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 4 p. (1 folded leaf); 18 x 23 cm. + envelope. Written in pen and black ink. (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Ruskin writes to Lupton at Russell Square. The letter is dated "Dec 6" although preserved with an envelope stamped "April" of 1855 or 1856. He refers to a plate that he has titled and directs Lupton to send it to Mr. Armytage for lettering. He says, of another plate, that he needs not touch it "for it wants much lightening." He specifies the changes he wants Lupton to make to the plate, pointing to lights "behind the church" and asking Lupton to follow "the shapes in the drawing." He remarks that Lupton needs to make some particular marks "look fasting into mere lines. Yours look all as if they had over-ate themselves--throw them all into a consumption." Ruskin adds a rough illustration to show what he intends. He follows with more specifications about lightening the image, and then tells Lupton, "When all this is done--Bring it out to me. I want a talk with you about next subject..." The letter appears unfinished, or closes abruptly, as Ruskin apparently meant to write on the last verso, but had unknowingly used for Lupton's letter the reverse of a letter already begun to a Mr. Le Keux. Ruskin scrawls, "I beg pardon didn't know of this" on this page, as though making apologies to Lupton. The letter to Le Keux is scratched out, but refers to other engravings, some depicting windmills and mountains. Le Keux engraved plates for Ruskin's fourth volume of Modern Painters, published in 1856, which likely dates the Lupton letter to 1855.
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, 1855 December 13; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 2 p. (1 leaf); 18 x 23 cm. Written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Ruskin writes that he will achieve a desired effect by "retouching [rather] than rebiting." He requests an impression of the plate in brown and another in grey, as well as the plate, "with a ground all over--for adding--not rebiting." He seems impatient, saying that he will send for the other impressions on the next day, but "I want this with all speed also."
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, 1855 December 18; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 p. (1 folded leaf); 19 x 23 cm. + envelope. Written in pen and black ink. (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Addressed to Lupton at Russell Square. Ruskin asks Lupton whether there is "any mistake about the tracing I sent to be rolled off" because he has apparently heard nothing about it and is concerned at the delay. Ruskin also asks about 50 impressions of another etching, and makes another request about it before it goes to press. Ruskin includes what appears to be a very loose sketch of one of the etchings in question.
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, [1855?]; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 2 p. (1 folded leaf); 18 x 23 cm. + envelope. Written in pen and black ink. (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Addressed to Lupton at Russell Square. Ruskin writes that he has been "saying such fine things of you in my preface to Mr. Gambart's book," a note that likely dates this letter to 1855, the year in which Ruskin penned a preface for Ernest Gambart's book, which was to contain several Turner prints. He follows with a report and instructions pertaining to the current state of their project. He asks to have 2500 copies of a particular etching, and says he wants to "enrich it a good deal before mezzotinting..." He asks whether it would not be best for Lupton to "finish off Gambart's plates" at this time, as he wants to "bring out that book this season..." He advises Lupton that "after the 5th you will have two...plates to do for me with all speed." Ruskin says that these plates "will be quite ready when Bolton is done."
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, [1855 or 1856]; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 2 p. (1 folded leaf); 18 x 23 cm. + envelope. Written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Ruskin writes with instructions about the biting of a particular plate, specifying that "none of it is to be darker than the etching of 'Taconay,' which is enclosed with it." The mention of Taconay, a mountain that Ruskin discusses in the third volume of Modern Painters, likely dates this letter to 1855 or 1856. Ruskin gives Lupton directions about the biting of the plate, referring to various parts of the image where different levels of lightness and darkness are needed. He requests four proofs of this plate when it is bitten.
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, [1855 or 1856]; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 2 p. (1 folded leaf); 18 x 23 cm. Written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Ruskin discusses ink colors, saying that "I have had my Stones of Venice in the most delicate lilac purple possible," and goes on to advise Lupton to ask a Mr Le Keux, who made a certain plate for the work, "about the best inks." He insists on having blue ink, saying that "it makes all the difference." He instructs Lupton not to touch the "Lombard Apennine," saying that it cannot be better. Ruskin asks for more proofs using the ink that Le Keux recommends. He closes by assuring Lupton that "all is done that there is haste for when [the] Apennine & St George are fairly at work." These pieces, which are "The Lombard Apennine" and "St. George of the Seaweed," were being prepared for the third volume of Ruskin's Modern Painters, which would be published in 1856.
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, 1856 January 14; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 3 p. (1 folded leaf); 18 x 23 cm. Written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Ruskin remarks that "we are most unlucky with each other." He describes material sent to Lupton, and gives directions about the biting of the etching. He asks Lupton to thank a Mr Smith for "his pains." He asks Lupton not to bite the current piece too far, as he can always rebite further. He says he does not plan to mezzotint this piece, for he does not have time. Ruskin encloses a rough sketch to show where he has made a correction. Ruskin compliments Lupton on his son's work, saying that it evidences "no want of industry--but too equally distributed & he has not yet taste for anything grand--Too fond of green & yellow--wants more purple & gray. But he will get on."
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, 1856 January 29; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 2 p. (1 leaf); 18 x 12 cm. + envelope. Written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Sent from Ruskin's home, Denmark Hill, and addressed to Lupton at Burchett's Park, Sussex. Ruskin writes to Lupton requesting further proofs of an item, and commenting upon a proof for "Bolton." He says that it lacks depth, and "looks as flat as pasteboard..." Ruskin also asks Lupton to letter a "mezzotint of the stones from Turner & Claude as enclosed," although this lettering is not revealed in the actual letter and may have been on a separate document now lost. Ruskin closes with a request for another etching, as he wants to refer to it (presumably as he was generating commentary for the "Harbours of England" series. He asks how long it will take for Lupton to "throw off 1500 copies of [his] mezzotints." The letter is rather business-like, as is characteristic of Ruskin's communications to Lupton at this time.
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, [1856?] February 19; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 p. (1 leaf); 17 x 20 cm. Written in pen and black ink. (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Written on pale blue ruled paper, dated "Feb 19." Ruskin writes to Lupton about the Bolton image, saying that they must finish it first, before other work can be done. He calls Lupton's attention to certain areas of the proof he has apparently received, remarking that "the dark mark of the flood-water on the rocks is harsh here." Ruskin describes his own end of the ongoing work and says that "By the time we are all right with this the other will be ready." He adds, after closing, a note about lettering for Lupton's and his own name.
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, 1856 February 28; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 p. (1 leaf); 18 x 23 cm. + envelope. Written in pen and black ink. (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Ruskin's letter accompanies a tracing apparently carried with this letter (not sent by post) and that he wishes Lupton to have "rolled off." He requests a "proof of the white cloudy one" on blue paper. He comments that the lettering is correct on a particular plate, but that he thinks the plate will still need retouching.
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, [1856] February 29; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 3 p. (1 folded leaf); 18 x 23 cm. + envelope. Written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Letter is addressed to Lupton at Russell Square. Ruskin writes to clarify a misunderstanding in some previous correspondence, saying that he seems "to have expressed myself so as to puzzle you." He requests fifty etchings to be taken off of the "present state of plate." He specifies a couple of small corrections to be made, and prints out the lettering that he wants Lupton to use for the plate's title. It reads: "Crests of La Cote and Taconay," which was an image in the fourth volume of Modern Painters, and thus dates this letter (given its February 29th notation) to 1856, a year in which there was a Leap Day and in which Ruskin was finishing work on the fourth volume of Modern Painters. Ruskin goes on to discuss having written to a Mr. Brookes to "get on..with mezzotint." He asks Lupton to wait to hear from him after having sent the proofs of "Bolton." Ruskin closes by suggesting that a plate with tracing can come "by bearer."
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, 1856 March 5; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 3 p. (1 folded leaf); 18 x 23 cm. + envelope. Written in pen and black ink. (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Addressed to Lupton at Russell Square. Ruskin writes that he is returning Lupton's proofs because he does not want "anything to do with them." He complains about Gambart's serious delay with a manuscript, and declares that he "won't countenance any further delay about the plates--except to take the rust off." After continuing to bemoan his difficulties with Gambart, Ruskin says that he is sending Lupton "the best windmill I have," but that he cannot have the "Margate" image or plate that he has, as he is only willing for it to go to London to be displayed at the Turner gallery there. Ruskin closes with further instructions for Lupton's work on certain Turner pieces that he terms "unfinished," saying that he only wants the rust taken off of them. He tells Lupton that he "may show Gambart this letter if you like."
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, [1856?] March 5; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 2 p. (1 folded leaf); 20 x 26 cm. + envelope. Written in pen and black ink on pale blue paper. (Box 1, Folder 31)
    Addressed to Lupton at Russell Square. Ruskin writes that "under the plate is the proof etching." He discusses retouching, and asks Lupton to bite the "piece marked very lightly as I think I have put too many lines in it." Other directions are conveyed about the etching. Ruskin then asks when Bolton will be done, and remarks that based on what Lupton has told him about the time required for the process, he feels he should put off mezzotinting until later. Ruskin gives several more instructions about the process of finishing this volume of the work, and then offers to work on the lettering (?) in some fashion "so that no time will be lost." He sends his compliments to Lupton's son. This letter, while only dated "March 5" on the envelope, likely dates to 1855 or 1856.
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, 1856 March; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 p. (1 leaf); 25 x 20 cm. + envelope. Written in pen and black ink. (Box 1, Folder 32)
    Addressed to Lupton at Russell Square. Ruskin writes: "let this have a lapdogs bite on the taille and a bulldogs on the foreground..." in a fanciful note of instruction to Lupton on the handling of a plate. He is impatient to get proofs and to have the plate grounded for mezzotint, "for I must not lose a moments more time on this plate." He says that he will let Lupton have a Turner piece to work from, although he must "insure it for half a million..." A letter in a somewhat unusually jovial tone from Ruskin, signed warmly, "ever yours affectionately, J Ruskin."
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, [1856?] May 19; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 p. (1 folded leaf); 21 x 14 cm. + envelope. Written in pen and black ink. (Box 1, Folder 33)
    Letter is dated "19th May" but preserved with envelope dated 24 December 1855. Ruskin discusses having sent etchings of "Chamonix and Chartruese, which are the two most important subjects..." and asks Lupton to "get them all done" by the time Ruskin returns in late August or September. Ruskin writes that he will lend plates of other items, but "not the etching, as it is quite irreplaceable." It is not entirely clear to which work these illustrations (of either locations or monasteries in France) belong, although Ruskin spent much time in Chamonix throughout his life. Ruskin asks for proofs to be sent to him at Basel. The tone of the letter is business-like, almost brusque in parts. Ruskin seems very invested in the smooth continuation of the project while he travels abroad. Ruskin's mention of his travel plans suggests that this letter dates from 1856, a year in which he and his parents stayed in Europe (particularly in Switzerland) from May to October.
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, 1856 October 17; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 2 p. (1 leaf); 18 x 23 cm. Written in pen and brown/black ink. Housed with other ALS of the same date. (Box 1, Folder 34)
    Ruskin apparently originally included a drawing with this letter, saying that he has just sent the outline of the same to Boys for etching. Ruskin notes that "it will serve you to rest yourself with, when you are tired of the glacier; or begin to feel that cloudy weather cold..." He asks Lupton, "can you mezzotint conveniently over a line engraving? And if a line engraving is on some plate with a mezzotint--could both be printed together?" Ruskin then asks Lupton if he can "pick up...an impression" of the vignette on page 214 of Samuel Rogers's from Poems, a volume published in 1856 and illustrated with designs by Turner and Stothard. Ruskin closes with a pen and ink sketch of the trellis that appears on this page of the Rogers book.
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, 1856 October 17; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 p. (1 folded leaf); 18 x 23 cm. + envelope. Written in pen and brown/black ink. Housed with other ALS of the same date. (Box 1, Folder 34)
    Ruskin writes Lupton to say that Boys will send or has already sent an etching of "blue mountains." He asks Lupton to have fifty copies sent to him before it is grounded. He requests that Lupton return another etching, and clears up some confusion over a previous request for an impression. Ruskin also remarks that he may prepare a "double plate for" Lupton, with "lighter subjects."
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, 1856 December 4; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 4 p. (1 folded leaf); 18 x 23 cm. + envelope. Written in pen and brown ink. (Box 1, Folder 35)
    This letter is addressed from Denmark Hill and sent to Lupton at Russell Square. It conveys an unusual, emotionally frank and open, message. Ruskin writes that he is sorry that Lupton has taken any trouble over their work at present. Lupton's wife Susannah died in 1856, and Ruskin attempts to offer his condolences, although he says that he did not write previously. Ruskin remarks that he is "the worst of all people to find comfort for others in any distress of this kind--for I never can find any, myself: In any loss of love I have had to sustain through life nothing but time, & labour, ever relieved me. I cannot look forward as many people do to another state. The next world is inconceivable to me and the darkness closes on me irrevocably. There are few--very few people, not among my own near relations, for whom I have more regard than for you--and indeed I have been deeply grieved to think that your cheerful & kindly face should never be touched with the same smile again--and that I had no power of helping you in any way. I am so accustomed, now, to feel the world getting emptier & gloomier about me--Turner's death, for one thing--having at once extinguished my fairest sunshine--& many other things happening one after another to depress me that I only keep up to the level of any daily work by daily work; & am a good deal harder & colder than I ought to be, at my age, & with what of natural sensibility I had once...but I still can feel for you and I hope you will believe that as far as my sympathy can be any good to you you may trust to it." Ruskin goes on to invite Lupton to see him when he is ready, and to "breathe the frosty air of the fields." He also conveys his regards to Lupton's son, Nevil.
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, [1856?]; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 p. (1 folded leaf); 18 x 23 cm. Written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 36)
    Ruskin instructs Lupton not to "touch that Bolton any more, it is quite beautiful." He requests six more proofs in brown, and instructs Lupton to add lettering after that. He gives an example of the proper lettering, and then thanks Lupton for his "expedition with" an etching "and the Bolton, both." He asks Lupton to send the next piece "when the ground is ready...for further touches."
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, 1857 February 11; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 2 p. (1 folded leaf); 18 x 23 cm. + envelope. Written in pen and black ink. (Box 1, Folder 37)
    Ruskin's letter is addressed to Lupton in Sussex, but then corrected to send to his address in Russell Square, London. Ruskin writes to Lupton expressing his frustration over Boys, another engraver. Ruskin complains, "I don't understand why Boys works so well for you--so ill for me--I think he must want to give me trouble because I am an 'amateur.'" Ruskin apparently sent with this letter one of Boys's engravings, and calls Lupton's attention to it in his message. Ruskin asks Lupton to speak to Boys and "find out what he really means." He then discusses the market value of Lupton's Turner etchings versus his own, saying that he is confident in the value of his collection. The envelope has many different inscriptions, one of which reads: "TAKE CARE of this/Mr Ruskin's letter to me TL." It is stamped many times, which suggests that the letter may have been misdirected at first.
  - Letter to Thomas Goff Lupton, 1858 December 4; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 p. (1 leaf); 18 x 23 cm. Written in pen and black ink. Housed with one undated ALS. (Box 1, Folder 38)